so no
we've spoken about meditation techniques
and methods
before we've covered that many times but
um
just as a to cover it again
maybe some become clearer to others
what is what do you think about
common meditation methods or techniques
such you know as i don't really want to
mention other people's names techniques but so
other people's names techniques but so
in general like
contemporary meditation techniques when
you google buddhism it's
meditation first thing that comes up
well that's the that's the point that
we've been making in all the previous
talks meditation really it's the
you cannot possibly you can possibly do
those practices without the implicit
view behind it view that certain performance
behind it view that certain performance
observance mechanical concentration
surrender to the perception
will somehow magically transcend you
into the spirit of knowledge
that is implicit so some people might
really have their view really developed
some people might not have it so firmly
developed but
if you think that um
meditation technique can somehow
result in some knowledge through itself
means you're partaking in that view
and that's why it's completely wrong
so really when it meditation technique
is not so much
well it is obviously about technique you
do but it's really
what's even more important is the view
you have behind it
so when we talk about meditation is not
a method
in other words uh regarding things as a
method is your view so that's why like when i
is your view so that's why like when i
remember in the past sometimes i
explained this to people and then it was
like ah okay so
your method is the no method method
it's like no that's not what i'm saying
because they would think that denial of
the methods
basically well they don't think they
take denial or refusal of the methods
they take it as another method
so that's what i mean it's on the level
of how you take things that you do
what is the implicit view what do you
believe those things can result in
that's where the problem is and that
problem sure is is made worse
when you blindly just follow a technique
as i said it already implies that view
and now you're just doubling down on it
to really not thinking for yourself but
the opposite trying to avoid all the
thinking and just concentrating
concentrate to watching your nostrils or i don't
to watching your nostrils or i don't
know whatever else contemporary
meditation might be making you do
so it's the view behind you want to see
that am i holding a view
that if i sit and concentrate on the
nostrils i will have an
experience of a special kind that will
somehow result in knowledge or feed and
result in knowledge or feed and
knowledge
and that's already the wrong view that's
already basically a factor of syllabus
my virtue my duty if i adhere to it
will result in wisdom and liberation
it's the first factor because of which
it you will not get
wisdom and liberation
so usually methods and practices are are
within that factor
and that's why people would often be
quite touchy about it as well
if somebody criticizes their meditation
method even if criticism is wrong
say somebody criticizes unjust love some
method are you emotionally feeling defensive
are you emotionally feeling defensive
means there is no dispassion there
so it's how you take things what you how
you regard them
how you what you assume behind them so
the point is then
not so much about what you do well what
you do is you keep the precepts
of course you restrain your senses
your eye your nose and so on you're
devoted to wakefulness is that what i
would say
so try to not lapse basically try to not
lose the sight of the context of your
situation that's already a form of samadhi
so now if you really want to develop the
samadhi that pertains to liberation well
you need the right view as some of the
suitor says there is no samadhi without
the right view
so it doesn't mean you shouldn't try but
what you want to understand is that
it's not about i'll try this technique
or try that technique it's about
i must try to basically uproot
my assumption of technique resulting in
knowledge and instead
see a direct way to knowledge whereby i
will know how to develop it
and and pursue it so that's
that's why it's always like he knows
that he knows for a sort of
for people who develop understanding
it's not like oh i watched my nostrils
then i had this super calming experience
he was just out of this world
and that's my knowledge no that's just a
novelty experience
knowledge is that which you understand
that you know how it comes about that's
what we say
you know the origin you know the uh the
uh the danger
you know the escape you know the
cessation all these things
means you fully understand it there is
no chance there or magical belief that
oh maybe hopefully it will happen like
this or happen like that
when i concentrate on this hopefully
this will arise no no you know exactly
if you attend to these things this is
where the mind is heading
if you don't attend to these things this
is where the mind is heading
that's what the clarity of awareness and
mindfulness is basically what somebody is composing
is basically what somebody is composing
that same mindfulness that you have
but that would be impossible for you to
do for as long as you don't abandon the
view of a method that i just described
of a method that i just described
if you still on the level of a view
assume or hold an assumption that if you
go through the right motions or attend
to right things
the knowledge will happen to you that's
why it won't happen to you
the only way for knowledge to happen to
you is to understand what knowledge is
and then to develop it through your own
effort so let's say that a person is doing
so let's say that a person is doing
he comes across mindfulness and
breathing but he doesn't have
that that view
that if i do this breathing step-by-step
technique breathing in 10 seconds and
breathing out 10 seconds whatever the
technique might be
he doesn't have the view that it will
lead to magical insights
or just how the blue is gonna he's gonna
be liberated
well that's yeah he doesn't need to have
such a coarse view that's
i wasn't i wasn't alluding at that
all you need to do is not know
where the place of mindfulness of
breeding is what what it does
and you won't be doing it rightly that's
why anapanasati is taught to those with
the right view
to you know to get rid of the remaining
answers and kilases so if you don't have
the right view
you have no panasonic basis for
anapanasati so
but then i consider well i don't have
the right view
but here's this anapanasati so let me
try and do it
well it will be impossible for you to do
it without the implicit view of a method
behind and that's why you will not be able to
and that's why you will not be able to
do it rightly when i say it will be
impossible for you to do it without
implicit view of the method in other
words i'm saying
it's impossible for you to do it without
your silabata paramasa
so if you want to even try anapanasati
rightly get the right view as in
abandon silabata paramasa that's why
that is
the first factor that's abandoned one of
the first three factors that is
abandoned for sotheban
and that's why yes there are no methods
for him because he sees directly
what partner ibana is not in a mystical
manner not in some
so magical transcendental kind of
outcome of certain practices no he understands
of certain practices no he understands
if i abstain from this and cultivate
this my mind will be liberated
as clear as a day he might be lazy
and negligent and not choose to abstain
from things
sufficiently enough so he might not
become another hunt in this life but
nevertheless he knows and he knows that
he knows
so all the previous talks if we do about
the method and techniques just bundle
all that into silhouette parameters
because that's what it is practically
speaking
but that's that method that technique
that fetter calms me down and i'm not
you know doing anything bad i'm not
drinking i'm keeping the precepts
whatever right i'm a good person yeah so it calms
right i'm a good person yeah so it calms
me down
that method yeah which is yeah better if
you want to be a good pluto you know
yeah you can do methods no problem but
we're not talking about that
we're talking about so
if you want to be calm good person that
doesn't drink and go out and
comes through concentrating on your
nostrils or you can do any concentration
and calming and breathing technique and
psychotherapy or whatever it's going to
make you a better
worldly person it's not going to free
you from the world
so don't conflate the two and then you
can decide for yourself what you want to
do
but that's that's what i'm saying the
worst is when you think you can have it
both ways
oh i know i don't know i know i don't
have a reference for what truly calm
mind is
what truly liberating mind is but this
suits me
this meditation suits me and i will do
it and i will also
kind of implicitly believe that it is
bringing me closer to nibana although i
have no reference point whatsoever
that's nothing other than wishful
thinking and again you can do
it if you want but it's actually if you
realize for yourself actually that's
quite a powerless thing
to perpetuate in my mind it is just
wishful thinking
so what about doing a technique
now that you've said that to me so i
still do my technique but i know that
i'm not free from suffering so
i'll keep doing my calm technique
calming technique of breathing
i know that i'm not free from something
i know that i don't have right view so
i'll keep an open mind
i mean yeah you have to start somewhere
i suppose but see your start there is
not with the technique you're doing
your start there is with what you just
heard i'm telling you
in other words even if you had no
technique whatever you were doing on a
kind of practice
was your technique so to speak even if
it wasn't very formally defined
you don't need to do anything to be
within the factor of virtue and
the duty of observance the duty of
concentration the duty of my seal and so
on
you are within it
so it's not about finding the the the
like the least harmful technique or
something like that no it's about
actually hearing uh the instruction they will
hearing uh the instruction they will
make you
think that's basically the context above
your technique oh
so whatever i'm doing is a technique but
how am i regarding it what is my view
behind it so even if you choose now after you
it so even if you choose now after you
heard me
what i just said to you if you choose to
adhere to your technique
well okay maybe you still don't have
faith in what i said so
you know you're doubtful but at least
use that okay so let me then think
what are my hopes assumptions
implications behind the technique i'm
doing what are my thoughts in regard to this
what are my thoughts in regard to this
what am i hoping to achieve
do i even know what my goal is of my own
meditation or i just sort of decided you know as
or i just sort of decided you know as
the day goes by
and depending on how i feel that time
do i know the outcome do i have the true
measure of wholesome calmness
whatever just calm in the same sense
you're calm after you wake up for
over after a full night of sleep
or am i calm because my mind cannot be
prepared by suffering and anything that
comes from the senses because i'm in
control of my senses which calmness is
it
am i calm because i've basically
surrounded myself with a soothing
environment that never challenges me
never disturbs my senses there is no
heat cold
insects other people voices sounds
noises or am i calm because all these things
or am i calm because all these things
when they arise i am unmoved by those
things
am i precious about my meditation time
like i must have my safe space where
nobody will disturb me so i can sit and
concentrate because there is no other
way i can concentrate
or i can concentrate at any in any given
scenario even if i end up in a hospital
immobile in a cast i can't move
surrounded by 50 other patients
because that's basically where your life
is heading
destruction so you will you will not be
able to exercise influence over your
to exercise influence over your
environment and circumstances for much
longer really
so if your meditation is always
dependent on the right circumstances
that's not meditation
that's literally just soothing and
covering up the wounds without actually
treating it
so let's say okay so i was doing a
meditation technique now i've heard what you've
technique now i've heard what you've
what you say and i
abandoned that technique of breathing
okay so what do you do now exactly
so now i'm trying to find out what is
right view yeah so i need to find out
what is right for you how do i get it
what is this
where do i start
well you start by by listening to more
of the instructions that directly in
their way
by by rereading the suitors that you
read before and new suitors that you
haven't read
with this new basically fresh set of
eyes so to speak
ah that's what you're looking for now
where the right view is
and then yeah but what else you do well
the buddha says what you do
restrained virtue seeing the danger in
the slightest fault
are you seeing the dangerous light as
well is there a context in your mind
that you invest
effort to maintain throughout the day
is it because by the way there is no
meditation without silo
so even if you disregard everything i'll
say about techniques if you get offended
or whatever else
doesn't matter ask yourself whatever
technique you're doing
is your sealer impeccable underneath it
or is your ceiling good enough so by
your own measure
so that you can go and develop your
perfect technique
because there is no meditation without
full restraint of the senses
so do you spend your day restrained
celibate withdrawn so even if we don't go into
withdrawn so even if we don't go into
debate over techniques has that
requirement been met
if no there is no discussion with you
then because whatever you talk about
meditation it's not what meditation is
because you basis for it it's basically
like when the
and the buddha said to the monk who was
asked about
what is the pleasure of being withdrawn
from sensuality and this man couldn't
quite explain anybody said well if you
fully understood it the similarities
that haven't had before you would have
they would have occurred to you and it
said imagine you come with a man to the
bottom of the hill
you climb to the top of the hill he
stays at the bottom and you tell him
oh dear friend the view from this top of
the hill it's immeasurable
i mean i can see the valleys and oceans
and forests it's just
heavenly and the man at the bottom turns
around and all he sees is tree trunks
and he says no i don't i don't i
disagree i don't see that
and then if this man had compassion for
the man at bottom you come down the hill
grab him by the arm drag him up the hill
and see for yourself and if the
simulator was being withdrawn from
sensuality you see
for yourself but most people are like
the man at the bottom
they argue the view from the top while
they're still deep down in the forest of
sensuality because that in itself is already a form
because that in itself is already a form
of meditation sense restraint
throughout the day you cannot possibly
do that without having developed proper
imperturbable mindfulness and what is
other what is imperturbable mindfulness other
what is imperturbable mindfulness other
than compose mindfulness
other than samadhi literally composure
keeping it together and that's that's
something you can actually get your
mind around so to speak you know don't
do anything wrong
yeah okay and always be aware at the
corner of your eye the background
in your mind so i'm about to do this i'm
doing this
the environment i'm in am i heading
towards the young wholesome
for wholesome if unwholesome make the
effort drain yourself
in pull yourself out so
that's where the work is done yeah so
when i said
yeah am i doing anything wrong or am i
going to do anything wrong
is there any unwholesome intentions here
yeah but that requires me to have a specific
but that requires me to have a specific
way of being aware yeah being aware of
the context that's what i keep saying
and by the way can you like if all you
do is concentrate what's in front of you
your intentions will become invisible to
you more than they already are
can never attend your intention
because the only reason you're attending
things is because you intended to do so
intended intention is always in the
background intention is always the state of mind
intention is always the state of mind
that's the whole
connection between chetan and chitta
etymologically speaking
intention and the mind so you want to be
aware of your intention exactly and
that's not something you concentrate on
that's only something you can know as
it's their enduring as a current context
of your experience
so this type of awareness
of being able to be aware of your
intentions behind your actions
it's a kind of basic
tool for a
person that's going to be wholesome
or responsible person yeah it's the
first step
of being self-aware perpetually
being something self-reliant so is your
constant practice of concentration again
in inverted commas
whatever it is is that improving that
self-awareness that you have throughout
the day
or is it making you completely like sort
of lapse
and go in a state of unawareness because
when the buddha described
how sariputta went through all the janas
he described that every single one of
those genres
the most refined ones were fully
understood fully known mindfulness was
clear as a day throughout it
so that can be another criteria if you
can't quite shake off your
doing the anapanasati or something well
make sure your self-awareness is not
compromised knowingly he breathes in knowingly he
knowingly he breathes in knowingly he
breathes out
so are you aware even more of your
current situation when you're doing your
technique method of meditation
or basically the world is shut down are
you are you ner
exactly well no that yeah that's what it
comes down i said that before yeah one
pointedness but is it one wide point that includes
but is it one wide point that includes
everything
or one narrow point that shuts
everything up
and if you when i read any like most of
the contemporary structures it was
always about the direction of shutting
everything else out
so that's why it goes hand in hand with
stop thinking stop thinking too much
thinking just focus just focus just concentrate
just focus just focus just concentrate
repeat the mantra concentrate
become basically a thoughtless half
asleep doing this thing doing this just do it
doing this thing doing this just do it
repetitively
until you go into that mental stupor so
to speak
so i want to develop the right view and
i start
restraining the sentence the slightest
faults you think
of the senses will already make you
wakeful mindful
and alert and that's already somatic to
begin with
and then within that like when that's
not taking too much of your energy when
the mind is established when there's
buddhism in mind is pliable and not
lighter and not heavy
then you could okay read the suttas take
other things that
in your mind need to be understood what
is suffering
what is the origin of suffering what is
the what is the basically
um any aspect
of the suttas they will be talking about
what is a nature what is dukkha what is
like understand it make the effort
within that
properly developed basis of sila sense
strength mindfulness and somali
so you are doing you wisdom practice now
am i trying to understand what am i
watching my nostrils because i'm
basically tired of trying to understand
and yes sometimes you might be tired of
trying to understand that's what i mean
it will be taking too much effort then
okay stop it but
that doesn't mean you stop your sense
restraint control of your senses and
they in daily mindfulness
so don't stop your samadhi you don't
stop your self-awareness
so yeah you don't have to actively if
you can if you cannot
but it doesn't mean oh but now i am
justified in going into the state of
oblivion i'm forgetting about myself
that's like what we spoke in another
talk i forgot the title like you never
rest it doesn't mean you always work just
it doesn't mean you always work just
simply means you refuse basically
even when you don't work you refuse to
give in to that distraction and
self-delusion where you forget about
yourself so in that sense you're always diligent
so in that sense you're always diligent
so you never rest
yet that type of basically effort is
effortless it doesn't tire you out distraction ties
it doesn't tire you out distraction ties
you out
sensuality ties you out misguided
advertising ties you out
mindfulness done rightly it's effortless
and you can't have too much of it
that's the way i would say so another
thing is you could reevaluate when you
when there are certain practices that
you find helpful
like what is helpful
to me what is the helpfulness aspect of
those practices
what is my measure for helpfulness
what's my criteria
what's my value easy car makes me feel
or do i see it
like genuinely supporting my sense
restraint composure
clarity of mindfulness in a day-to-day
life or i don't quite see it and if you don't
or i don't quite see it and if you don't
make the effort to see it
in itself it cannot present itself to
you you need to do it
so how does this
seeing the danger in the slightest fault
sense restraints
relate to yoni so maniscade
well it's that we said that that first
step in
having the knowledge of the context and
not being absorbed in the object of your
concentration or attention
knowing where your intentions are
that's already the beginning of yours
enduring because they are there enduring
so knowing the background discerning the
peripheral
that's that's pretty much it and that's
why if you practice that you will get to
see the sign of your mind
the more clear
seeing of your intentions you are
chaitanya the clearer cheetah will
become outlined
and the clearer the the setup is
what sort of the framework of experience
the the well that's what the mind is yeah so
the well that's what the mind is yeah so
that's what i mean the setup or the
the way things are situated
yeah and that's determined basically
pretty much by the state of the mind
that's where the mind is the forerunner
and that's where the prerequisite for
the right view is that grasping the sign
of your mind the outlines of your mind
seeing it for what it is and during
there not abstractly not as a speculative
not abstractly not as a speculative
thought
not as a mystical experience at the end
of your concentration effort no right
there and then
my mind is such and you see it you see
the suchness of it
and you don't interfere with it the
state of mind
is first that you by the way did not
create you're subjected to it in the same sense
you're subjected to it in the same sense
we're subjected to this weather
it comes and goes it arises it ceases it
increases it decreases doesn't matter
but the point is for somebody who
doesn't see
sign of their mind doesn't see the mind
in suchness as enduring a lady mind is
elated mind depressed mind is depressed
my happy mind is heavy mind
is saying they put themselves first
so if i own this mind this mind is mine
and that's why you suffer when the mind
that you don't want basically is
directing in the direction that it's
unpleasant and and you you're being influenced and
and and you you're being influenced and
pressured and affected by the unpleasant
state of mind by not as lofty as you
wanted to be not as light as you wanted
to be not as
motivated as you wanted to be but if you
were to just see mind for what it is you
would not be affected by it
it's only because you keep implicitly
sort of entertaining the notion of
ownership of it
so once you are familiar with that
order well that's yes you need to
cultivate it
it's not like one and done deal like you
see it once and it's done finished
you see once and you have to then keep
restoring the order because
your habits your will keep sort
of washing your way away from that order
into the wrong order so to speak
same like going against the stream you
have to
sort of uh persist
in even application of effort to go
against the stream until you reach the
end of that stream
if your effort lapses this stream will
pick you up and drag you down again
so same with the right order you need to
sustain it
but seeing the right order on the basis
of seeing your mind in its suchness
is the beginning towards the right view
and that's why that's what the right
view is derived seeing the right order
knowing what comes first that's why
those people who
got the right view of the buddha would
would speak is like oh it's amazing
it's like master gautama putting first
that which was second
and put in second that which was first
putting that which was upside down
putting down and that which was down
putting up
ah fixing it turning upright
and that's where you would know now what
to do
sustain protect and develop that order
which is the noble little path
don't cause the disorder through lust
aversion distraction through intentions
based on lust aversion and distraction
abstain from it and this order will
become solid refined so where does
then anapanasathi come in well panasati
comes into for somebody who understood
the right order
and they want to develop the further
calmness of the mind
the the further like a
non-perturbability of their mindfulness
because that's what anapanasati
fortifies your satipatanas
they have brought to fulfillment through
through your so instead of
so it's basically just doing the same
practice of mindfulness of sati patana
just doing it on the level of your
breath that's it that's what on a
panasonic is it's the same practice
just instead of going up and down and
about you just sit still and you do it
within this but it's the same practice
that's what i said when like that body
what i said when like that body
that's there when you're mindful of your
breath is body that stands for the body
body among bodies how it's translated
and you
you're mindful of that body correctly
means you're seeing the characteristics
of the body correctly
the suchness of it without your honesty
without your interference
you stay with that site long enough any
notion of ownership and interference
will fade away any notion of lust
will fade away and notion appropriation
will fade away yeah that's so that's
that's based upon this
based upon this
prerequisite it should be done on this
prerequisite of
seeing the minds well regardless of
which concentration you do it's all about
concentration you do it's all about
fortifying your mindfulness you know the
mindfulness that you supposedly have
before your concentration
if you read a certain you'll see
basically that mindfulness
is that which gets developed to the
extent necessary for the final knowledge
either through through sharp wisdom
other through through
the true sense restraint determination
and so on samadhi
any form of samadhi it's basically done
rightly it's the samadhi that fortifies
your mindfulness
the clarity of your recollection and
your awareness
self-awareness so you ask yourself
with your current practice of meditation
is your concentration
fortifying your day-to-day mindfulness
or is it completely opposite direction
of it
like you emerge from your concentration
and now you may start making the effort
to be mindful and be present and be
aware of your intentions
well that's what your samadhi should be
fortifying not something else
whether it's with personal whether it's
ahmadi either way basically you're
developing one brings the other whether
you're making effort actively to
understand or just through fortifying your
or just through fortifying your
mindfulness without active contemplation
you're developing the same understanding
but you know with introduction of more
and more commentaries and
interpretations and obviously two and a
half millennia
now it's like this this whole view of oh
this is my study this is my form
for my formal practice my mantra my this
and you have no idea how any of that
relates you just hope that all these
things that make you feel good make you
feel buddhist and a committed
practitioner will somehow result in your
will somehow result in your
enlightenment it's no different than to
like you know when martial arts back in
the day
existed originated in a form of
self-defense or during the war time but then a couple
or during the war time but then a couple
of millennia they got so mystified and
our people have these hollow forms doing
these holo forms
unable like to even defend themselves
there's no practical value of it
so that's it like formal meditation
today is completely the opposite of your
is completely the opposite of your
self-defense
that you would apply in the day which is
sense restraint and your mindfulness
and your awareness of your intentions so
why do you do it then
why don't you just find a self-defense
class they will teach you self-defense
as opposed to like
venerating some two years old two
millennial tradition there's divorce
from practicality
and then go and have to do the actual
self defense so that's what i mean
yeah do your samadhi as much as you want
but do it in a sense that you can sustain
do it in a sense that you can sustain
that throughout your day even when
you're not sitting
in your protected safe environment
that's the samadhi you should cultivate
that's the somali that's at least closer
to make you imperturbable
eventually you're mindfulness in
particular not like oh now
i am justified in in like basically
shutting everything else out and
engaging in my practice of concentration
to calm myself down
but then when i re-emerge from my formal
practice now i have to restart my mindfulness my
now i have to restart my mindfulness my
sense restraint
and remind myself of the values i need
to pertain to maintain throughout the
day as a form of self-defense
that's not the samadhi then you should
be cultivating as simple as that
go straight cutting with that which will
basically develop further that which you want to
develop further that which you want to
develop so do a meditation
as i said that you can then spread
throughout your day
even when you're not formally sitting so
then it is there should be no difference
between formal and environmental
it's the same thing it's the same thing
your body is just
what i've said so many times so many
times like
he establishes his mind in jhana you
know the perfect context withdrawn from
the perfect context withdrawn from
sensuality imperturbible
and then whether he sits eats goes to
toilet extends his arm whatever he does is
extends his arm whatever he does is
divine because the
state of his mind is divine second john
third same so there you go
establish your money john and then go
about and see how long your jhana will
last
so that again if you don't take anything
i say
well this should at least you could
reason that this is the right thing to
do
so even if you disagree with everything
else
the the the advice that your meditation
should basically theoretically
be sustainable throughout your day
throughout your time and should
certainly be in should be improving your
mindfulness and everything else
that is a valid like you cannot find
fault with that
if you don't take anything else i say
well at least use this and
revise your meditation practice
and by the way it doesn't matter oh i
must find out this teacher is wrong that
if that's only relevant
what's relevant is why you are doing it
for yourself
are you aware of the motives behind and
how you're doing it what's your
as i said implication of the method
behind are you hoping it will magically result
are you hoping it will magically result
or protect you or whatever else
in by some sort of lofty development as
a product of it or
but do you see it no are you are you
losing yourself awareness when you're
practicing it
or are you increasing yourself awareness
when even when you stop practicing it on
account of your previous practice
are your intentions cleared to spot as a
result of your samadhi practice
beforehand or you have to redo the same effort
or you have to redo the same effort
every time
you can't find fault with that because
that's exactly what everybody was saying
you should always know what you're doing
while you're doing and abstain from
doing unholes
and cultivate holes you should never
lose that context at the back of your
mind so no amount of samadhi and
so no amount of samadhi and
concentration is justifiable
to take you away from that
and then you realize oh yeah quite the
opposite samadhi in consideration should
be bringing you even closer
to knowing those things so easier
samadhi bringing you closer to knowing
the states of your mind knowing your
intention behind
actions when you're not sitting and
meditating continuously
how continuous that practice is
how continuously can you do it or you
can only do it when you're in a
protected environment
so if you are overdoing your
concentration with this new value
of finding the common ground that you
can sustain whether formal or informal
it will basically pull you out of your
over overdoing extent
so to speak if you were overdoing it
before now when you realize oh but i
should be able to extend it throughout
the day
you will step back from that overly
concentrated self
like absorb where you lose the sight of
your situation and when you pull back
into that
okay so that's to the extent i can
practice these calming techniques and so
on
without over committing and actually
even when i'm not
and end up sitting and meditating i can
still sustain the same
self-awareness so that's composure
literally keeping it together
but you wouldn't say to somebody oh you
can keep things together
when you shut everybody out lock
yourself inside spend three hours
preparing and then no
means you're quite precious the one who
in the midst of things falling apart
keeps it together
is the one who can keep it together he's
the one who has somebody
even in colloquial times
hey keep it together man when people
said yes i can keep it together as long
as i'm
shutting my room which smells like sauce
it's only relative and i'm really
keeping it together
you want to keep it together regardless
of the circumstances that is the
impertilable somatic
the unshakeable mindfulness
that's it so that
single-handedly will make you stop
thinking overthinking about methods
methods and techniques because it's your
dialogue actually you realize
do i watch my nostrils for four seconds
or eight seconds that only matters to
somebody who hopes it is
magical um magical product results a
result of their concentration mystical result
of their concentration mystical result
basically they will be equated with
knowledge and wisdom and liberation
no
so realize most of it doesn't matter
what matters is you're making the effort
to sustain your mindfulness in
controlled environment and less
controlled environment
informal environment or informal
environment same iphones
because it's the same mind by the way
same awareness for alert yeah
so if you can if you can develop if you
can talk if you can only
uh sustain it in a protected environment
okay but you recognize it okay so it's
quite dependent on certain circumstances
which means
if those circumstances change my
mindfulness will go and i better make
further effort
to approve that dependence otherwise if
i'm not able to
to you know meet my requirements i will
fall apart
and then my sense restraint will suffer
my sea level suffer and everything else
will stop